{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Phosphorus vapour comprises of", "opta": "P", "optb": "P2", "optc": "P3", "optd": "P4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Conversion of yellow phosphorous to red phosphorous is done by heating it in covered retorts at __________ \u00b0C in absence of air.", "opta": "50-80", "optb": "250-400", "optc": "1000-1200", "optd": "800-900", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Commercial fertilisers are available mostly in the form of", "opta": "powder", "optb": "grannules", "optc": "lumps", "optd": "flakes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "All the nitrogenous fertilisers are not soluble in water.", "optb": "A straight fertiliser contains only one nutrient.", "optc": "Calcium cynamide is used as weed killer in onion fields.", "optd": "The phosphorous nutrient makes the plant stem stronger and increases its branches.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ammonia synthesis gas is produced from natural gas by", "opta": "thermal cracking", "optb": "steam reforming", "optc": "partial oxidation", "optd": "hydrogenation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catalyst used in the manufacture of NH3 by Haber's process is finely divided", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "iron", "optc": "vanadium pentoxide", "optd": "alumina", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Red phosphorous is changed into white phosphorous by", "opta": "heating in presence of light.", "optb": "melting under pressure.", "optc": "vaporisation followed by condensation.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Urea is represented as", "opta": "NH2.CO.NH2", "optb": "NH3CO.CH3", "optc": "NH.CO2.NH", "optd": "NH3.CO2.NH3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Two gas based fertiliser plants are located in", "opta": "Maharashtra and Gujarat", "optb": "Maharashtra and Orissa", "optc": "Gujarat and Madhya Pradesh", "optd": "Jharkhand and Chattisgarh", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fertiliser plants get their N2 requirements", "opta": "by fractionation of liquified air.", "optb": "by dissociating oxides of nitrogen.", "optc": "from coal gas (coke oven gas).", "optd": "from producer gas.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "During conversion of ammonium carbamate into urea, presence of large excess of water", "opta": "increases the yield of urea.", "optb": "adversely affects the yield of urea.", "optc": "reduces the evaporator load by diluting the urea solution.", "optd": "does not affect the yield of urea.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Hydrogen content of coke oven gas is __________ percent.", "opta": "4", "optb": "22", "optc": "58", "optd": "84", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "'Green acid' is the other name of phosphoric acid produced by the reaction of phosphate rock & sulphuric acid.", "optb": "Chemically unreactive nature of red phosphorous is due to its polymeric structure.", "optc": "Red phosphorous is the most reactive allotropic form of phosphorous.", "optd": "Red phosphorous, which is used in the manufacture of safety matches, is converted into white phosphorous by vaporisation followed by condensation.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ammonium nitrate (a fertiliser) is coated with limestone powder to", "opta": "increase its nitrogen content.", "optb": "cut down its production cost.", "optc": "avoid the risk of explosion.", "optd": "add extra nutrient as fertiliser.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Action of phosphoric acid on rock phosphate produces", "opta": "superphosphate", "optb": "triple superphosphate", "optc": "nitrophosphate", "optd": "diammonium phosphate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reaction of dilute sulphuric acid with phosphate rock produces", "opta": "phosphoric acid", "optb": "superphosphate", "optc": "triple superphosphate", "optd": "gypsum", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Phosphoric acid is produced in wet process from phosphate rock and", "opta": "dilute H2SO4", "optb": "concentrated H2SO4", "optc": "concentrated NHO3", "optd": "concentrated HCl", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Base suspension fertiliser essentially contains", "opta": "13% N2 and 43% P2O5", "optb": "43% N2 and 13% P2O5", "optc": "43% N2 and 13% K2O", "optd": "43% K2O and 43% P2O5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Conditioners like finely divided peat are added to the fertiliser to", "opta": "counteract burning.", "optb": "avoid caking & hardening.", "optc": "produce bulk.", "optd": "increase its solubility.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Liquid ammonia is not used as such a fertiliser in tropical countries like India, because", "opta": "its N2 content is very low.", "optb": "it is very costly.", "optc": "it will evaporate on spraying.", "optd": "it is not available.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick out the wrong statement.", "opta": "Yellow phosphorous which is the most reactive allotropic form of phosphorous is transported under water.", "optb": "Apatite is the principal material present in phosphate rock which is chemically Ca10 (PO4)6 (F, Cl, OH).", "optc": "Urea is more hygroscopic than ammonium nitrate.", "optd": "Nitrogen fixation means the process of bringing atmospheric nitrogen into combination i.e. into nitrogen compound form.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following does not come under the category of 'secondary nutrient' for plant growth?", "opta": "Calcium", "optb": "Magnesium", "optc": "Sulphur", "optd": "Oxygen", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Steam reforming of naphtha is a source of hydrogen production for nitrogeneous fertiliser industry. What is the usual ratio of steam to carbon maintained in the process of steam reforming of naphtha ?", "opta": "1.5:1", "optb": "3.5:1", "optc": "10:1", "optd": "15:1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "(CH3 C6 H4)3 PO4 is the chemical formula of", "opta": "triple superphosphate", "optb": "tricresyl phosphate", "optc": "flourapatite", "optd": "superphosphate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is a catalyst promoter used in catalytic ammonia synthesis reaction ?", "opta": "Al2O3", "optb": "Cr2O3", "optc": "K2O", "optd": "MnO", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The concentration (weight %) of nitric acid produced by the oxidation of ammonia and absorption of nitrogen oxides with water is about __________ percent.", "opta": "60", "optb": "30", "optc": "95", "optd": "100", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Urea is a __________ fertiliser.", "opta": "nitrogenous", "optb": "potassic", "optc": "phosphatic", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Calcium ammonium nitrate (CAN) is", "opta": "a mixed fertiliser", "optb": "a straight fertiliser", "optc": "a complex fertiliser", "optd": "not a fertiliser ; it is an explosive", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "CO2 present in reformed gas (obtained by steam reforming of naphtha) is removed by absorbing in", "opta": "mono-ethanolamine (MEA)", "optb": "slaked lime", "optc": "ammoniacal liquor", "optd": "Methyl-Ethyl Ketone (MEK)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which is the most suitable fertiliser for paddy ?", "opta": "CAN", "optb": "Ammonium sulphate", "optc": "Ammonium nitrate", "optd": "Superphosphate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ammonium sulphate fertiliser is", "opta": "the highest concentration nitrogenous fertiliser.", "optb": "the best fertiliser for paddy.", "optc": "a basic fertiliser.", "optd": "a neutral fertiliser.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Lower temperature and large excess of ammonia in urea melt", "opta": "increases biuret formation", "optb": "decreases biuret formation", "optc": "is undersirable", "optd": "does not effect biuret formation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Superphosphate is manufactured by reacting phosphate rock with", "opta": "acetic acid", "optb": "sulphuric acid", "optc": "aluminium chloride", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vetrocoke solution is", "opta": "a mixture of K2CO3 and As2O3.", "optb": "K2SO4.", "optc": "a mixture of Na2CO3 and As2O3.", "optd": "Na2SO4.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In calcium ammonium nitrate (CAN) fertil-ser", "opta": "nitrate nitrogen is quick acting", "optb": "ammoniacal nitrogen is quick acting", "optc": "nitrate nitrogen is slower acting", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "P2O5 content in triple superphosphate is about __________ percent.", "opta": "42-50", "optb": "15-20", "optc": "85-90", "optd": "70-75", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "H3PO4 is the chemical formula of __________ phosphoric acid.", "opta": "pyro", "optb": "ortho", "optc": "meta", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Heating of orthophosphoric acid to 250\u00b0C produces", "opta": "metaphosphoric acid", "optb": "pyrophosphoric acid", "optc": "no change in it", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Vapor phase reaction of ammonia & nitric acid to produce ammonium nitrate is termed as the __________ process.", "opta": "Haber's", "optb": "Stengel", "optc": "Le-chatlier's", "optd": "Du-pont's", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Use of catalyst is a must in the ammonia manufacture, because the reaction is reversible as well as the heat of dissociation of N2 & H2 is high. The presence of promoter along with the catalyst helps in __________ of the catalyst.", "opta": "stabilisation", "optb": "increasing the effectiveness", "optc": "improving the strength & heat resistance", "optd": "all a, b & c", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Prilling tower is found in the flowsheet for the manufacture of", "opta": "ammonia", "optb": "urea", "optc": "superphosphate", "optd": "triple superphosphate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Reaction of orthophosphoric acid with soda ash produces", "opta": "sodium tripolyphosphate (STPP)", "optb": "tricresyl phosphate", "optc": "tributyl phosphate", "optd": "nitrophosphate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Urea is formed only", "opta": "in liquid phase", "optb": "in vapour phase", "optc": "at very high temperature", "optd": "at very low pressure (vacuum)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Dehydration of ammonium carbamate (to produce urea) is a/an __________ reaction.", "opta": "reversible", "optb": "catalytic", "optc": "exothermic", "optd": "endothermic", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Electric process as compared to wet process (for the manufacture of phosphoric acid)", "opta": "can use only high grade phosphate rock.", "optb": "is used less frequently.", "optc": "produces a valuable by-product called gypsum.", "optd": "is weak acid process.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ammonium sulphate can be produced by reacting gypsum with", "opta": "ammonia", "optb": "ammonium carbonate", "optc": "nitric acid", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nitrogenous fertiliser is required", "opta": "during the early stage of growth to promote development of stem and leaves.", "optb": "for accelerating fruit formation in later stage of growth.", "optc": "to lessen the effect of excessive potash application.", "optd": "none of these.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Fertiliser plant making ammonium sulphate employing gypsum-ammonia reaction (usual practice is to use ammonia and sulphuric acid) is located at", "opta": "Rourkela (under SAIL)", "optb": "Bokaro (under SAIL)", "optc": "Sindri (under FCI)", "optd": "Baroda (under G.S.F.C.)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Catalyst used in Haber's process for ammonia production is", "opta": "reduced iron oxide", "optb": "nickel", "optc": "vanadium pentoxide", "optd": "silica gel", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Sodium tri poly phosphate (STPP) is manufactured by reaction of phosphoric acid with sodium", "opta": "carbonate", "optb": "phosphate", "optc": "bicarbonate", "optd": "silicate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}